Hello and welcome back to Python Core and Applied Concepts.
So in today's lecture, we will be talking about expression which is the most natural
next big concept in any programming language.
So yeah, so let's begin the description by recapping what we just know recapping what
we discussed in the previous lecture, let me go to the slide here.
So this is a quick recap from our previous lecture, so what we discussed till now was you
know about the syntax and semantics of any programming language.
We said that no matter what programming language you want to study, you should always
focus on all these two big concepts of syntax and semantics and try to learn the language
by learning syntax and semantics.
So that's what we will be doing today also, we will start with how to write and build
correct expression inside Python and then we will talk about what these expressions actually
mean.
So no, how what they evaluate to, but we also talked about in the last lecture the concept
of variables and type systems which are again the starting point in any programming language
if you want to store values and manipulate them to compute something meaningful, then
you need to have this concept of variable.
So this concept of variable is very quote to any imperative programming language, though
in functional programming language as we don't have the notion of variable as it is in imperative
programming language, at least I mean variable don't help you change the state of the machine
there.
So this is a distinctive thing in an imperative programming language.
So we have seen it in the last lecture and we also saw how variable can point to objects
of different types or you know data types of which are you know essentially of different
types like integer string, Boolean values, etc.
So let's now take this forward today and try to build some more complex expression
or complex entities in our programming language which is very much useful if you want to do
any you know complex computation or computing if you want to write a function to compute any
complex function, then you know these variables and this basic data type cannot or may not
help you to a larger extent.
So that's why I mean the notion of expression is important because this gives you a method
to build more complex things out of these variables and type system.
So this is what we will be doing today, let me put to the next slide.
So this is in a nutshell what expression is, okay so this is no part of the grammar
to form from simple value complex logic, okay so we want to know you know form complex
logic, no complex thing which represent you know some let's say value when you compute
them.
So that's for that reason we need no expression.
So an expression is a combination of values variables and operators that can be evaluated
to produce a single resultant value.
So this is important I mean expression will always you know evaluate to some value, okay
so and you know this is very important as we will see I mean in letter today in the
lecture that statements and other you know statement in programming language need not
always you know evaluate to some value but when we talk about this concept of expression
the semantics of expression comes from what value it actually evaluates to, okay so
the meaning of expression is only in the value.
So if the expression evaluates to some value then we can assign you know that value as
the meaning to the expression, okay so let's know so yeah this is what we I said just
know that no so in contrast with statement I mean these things will always have value.
So this is the rough you know progression that we will follow in today's lecture so
we will start with basic you know expression and how to define them we'll learn about operators
different type of operator that is available there in Python and then we will talk about
a very special kind of expression which we call assignment expression and finally we will
conclude this lecture with the discussion around lambda expression so lambda expressions are
also very interesting and the origin can be you know trace to functional programming languages
so we'll very briefly look at what these lambda expressions are and how they can be useful
in certain you know instances, okay so now without knowing any further delay let's move to
the Jupyter Notebook and begin our discussion of expressions, okay so we are on our Jupyter Notebook
so you know let me begin by giving you some very small example of what an expression will look like
so for example I mean let's start with very basic mathematical operator and how to build
you know small mathematical expressions out of you know simple data types like you know integer,
okay so for to begin with let's you know start with these arithmetic operators and we know
from mathematics that now there are so many arithmetic operators that we can use to combine
no natural numbers or you know real numbers right I mean for example no addition is one
arithmetic operator, subtraction is another arithmetic operator multiplication no division
flow division model and exponent so these are also available in Python so if you want to you know
mimic these let's say mathematical operations and somehow implement them inside Python you can
actually use these you know operator to you know build expressions mathematical expressions in
inside Python so let me write some simple mathematical expressions for example let me you know
use this addition to so let's write it so let's try to no print what will happen if I let's say
no add 10 and 3 okay so we just want to see whether I mean this is accepted by Python or not so
is it a valid so right now what we are checking is is it a valid expression at all I mean
does this plus is recognized in the same way as we understand it mathematics or it has some
no different semantics so if you know I can you know run this then I know it's clear that Python
accept this as a you know correct syntax and if you get the intended value so what you can
infer is that the meaning is also same as you understand no addition to be so when we print
this what do we get so let me print it is 30 right so Python accepted this syntax and also give a
response which is 13 which closely matches you know your understanding of the addition right so
so what about now if I want to let's say or use this maybe division operator
is this division operator same as we expect or it's some different division operator so
what do you know in guess here I mean if I so this is exact division operator right which
you maybe want to use at this moment so this symbol actually represented division operator okay
so what about the no but the similar looking operator which I have written here so let's say
if I do the same division but now if I use this one which I call flow division so
or what do you expect what shall we get at this moment so you see there is a no clear difference
and this is exactly what we call flow division right I mean you know forget everything which
is after this no floating point okay so so after decimal I mean we forget everything so
right so if when you try to evaluate this expression the meaning is that you get the flow
no division so similarly can we go and do some more just let's no experiment with a few more
arithmetic expression to see whether we understand them properly so what about
this modular division so okay so what will with the result when you divide 10 by 3 so what
will be the final you know remainder that you get okay so that's what we can expect here right
so this this represent no modular division and you see when you divide 10 by 3 so the remainder
that you get is 1 right okay so so it's very you know important to you know keep in mind the
distinction between these two these three so first one is no normal division operator the second
one is flow division and the third one which you know uses you know this symbol actually builds
an expression that evaluates to remainder okay so what about this exponent so so let's not
try to see if you use this exponent so if I want to raise 1 to 2 get set 3
so this is also accepted right so what we saw just now was that no all the arithmetic
operation that we are used to in any mathematical computation are also available in Python
and these are the you know precise syntax and they're corresponding semantics so semantics matches
the semantic that we have in mind and the syntax is you know accepted by this programming language
which is Python so now let's move to some you know other type of you know expressions you know
which are you know for logical expressions okay so logical expression may not you know makes
sense to you know many of you who has not come from programming background because you know you
normally don't need them when you do you know mathematical computation or calculation because
we mostly you know we are confined to functions which calculate over natural number and
those you know can be easily captured using expressions that we have you know discussed
still now I mean these are arithmetic expression but this you know Boolean expressions are very
essential if you want to automate the process of computing so what do I mean by automating the
process of computing so let's say I mean your complex you know chain of computation that you want
mimic by writing a program if you have to decide at certain you know point or you have to take
a call at a particular place in the computation that which brands I sell go I sell I so if some
condition is true you may want to you know execute a set of instruction but if that condition is
not true in the other case you may want to no execute some other type of you know instructions
so this is called you know conditional and we'll come to it in the upcoming legend so to decide
so what will you decide based on right so you will decide based on what is the state of
computation okay and for taking this decision this you know logical expression this expression which
contain this or they have this logical you know connectives or operator will be very useful okay
so there are you know two you know primitive Boolean values which is available inside Python
which are called true and false and we'll see that we we can combine these you know kind of
Boolean values in meaningful ways to obtain more let's say complex you know unit for reasoning
or deciding at a particular time what we want to do okay so these are called AND or and not
operator they actually combine these no Boolean values to give you some you know output value so
for example no we have already seen right this type of true is bull it means I mean true is a
Boolean value okay so true similarly you know if false is also Boolean value but we can also
combine you know true and false using some Boolean operator or logical operator okay so one of them
is like I mean AND okay so let me now print so what will happen if I let's say
try to do this so so remember that I mean this will not be accepted by you know Python
interpreter if either syntax is you know wrong so if the syntax is wrong certainly it will not
be you know accepted so if say it passes this interpreter it means the syntax is correct and if
you get the same result as you know you want then you will you can be assured that the
semantics is also what you understand it okay so for example if I try to combine this true
and false let's say using AND operator so what will what do you expect so and operator combines
no two logical expression and it will evaluate to true only if you know both of them are true
otherwise if even if you know one of these bull logical expressions is let's say evaluates to
false then this thing will certainly give you a false right so when we try to evaluate it what do
we get we get a false value right which is you know what we know expected so but what about
this or operator so if we let's say to the same thing let me copy it
so when we you know just combine these two Boolean values with or you you get a true value
right and this is the this is the intuition that we have in mind about or right so when we say
either this or this so I will be happy if either this or this is true it means that you are
know ready to accept true value whenever one of these things you know become true right so this
exactly matches you know our you know intuition of or so what about not so if you know apply now
let's say let me get this and then so what if we you know to print let me use not of false
so what do you expect here I mean if you want to you know negate a false so what can I expect
so negation of a fault will naturally give us a true right so do we get exactly yeah so this is
what we get here right so so everything you know matches our intuition and our understanding
semantics of you know these true and false and how these logical connectives can be used to
you know combine them to get what you expect okay but no the question come that comes at this
particular point in time is that how will we even you know get this true and false I mean because
we don't explicitly want to write maybe true and false inside our program okay at a particular
place if you want to check some conditions and then decide whether we should not take one set of
action or another set of action most probably we will we would be interested in you know a condition
which are you know derived from comparing the variables or the value of variable that is
no present at particular point of time okay so at that point of time so for that you you need
this comparison operator okay so the comparison operator are actually the reason or you know
the primary way to you know get this you know true or false value okay so you don't get true
and false by just writing not true and false you know normally we don't want to use you know
these logical expression in that way we would like to derive these logical expression from
variables which are existing in the program and by comparing their value okay so this comparison
operator then you know turns out to be very useful so what a comparison operator they help us
compare the state of you know this variable or the values of the variable with each other
and then figure out whether you know our condition is true or not okay so so let me you know
and discuss some of the comparison operator that is available in Python programming language the
the very first one is this equality so if you want to check whether the value of one variable is
equal to value of you know another variable most probably we will be using this equality okay so
how to let me
and do some easy checks for you here
so you can know directly also you know compare some where we can
so no for example let me keep some value in this variable let's say no x
and then we go to another variable which is let's say no value 20 and now if I say x is equal
to is equal to y and let's say if I want to print this thing so what do you expect at this
particular no in this particular no code block what we have done is we instantiated x with
value 10 and the variable y be instantiated with value 20 and then we are checking whether their values
are same or not so so what is now our expected you know result at this point of time so
it's false right because the value of x and y are not same so remember you know this this is
you know comparison operator and not an assignment operator so some of you who have never done
programming I mean you may be confused at this point of time so in mathematics when we do
mathematics normally we we are always you know comparing things with you know each other when
we okay so so there is nothing called you know an assignment in mathematics this is very unique
to programming so because you want to store values you know somewhere in your memory so that's why
you are doing assignment but when we use this you know are two equal to science together we what
we mean is that we this becomes a logical expression this is you know no more a normal statement okay
but on the other hand side have any if you look at this this is a you know a statement proper
statement in programming language this is also an statement and both of this actually changes the
you know state of machine no so so your first statement this changes the state of your abstract
machine where the variables value you know gets changed to 10 whatever it was before you don't
care I mean at this after execution of this you know instruction it gets changed to 10 similarly
the you know assignment instruction y is equal to 20 changes the state of machine and makes it to
you know 20 without changing the value of x okay so but here I mean when you you know print this
this does not changes the state of machine okay so this is just so what is the effect of this
you will evaluate this particular expression and the value that you you are getting is you know
printed on the console so okay so this is a distinction between this
combat let me yeah let me show what we so so the another one is not equal to okay and not
equal to returns you true when both the numbers are not equal to so so let me you know again use this
second so we knew here that x was not equal to the height y so what answers I
as a line I expected this particular you know point so if I you know executed what do you expect
so the previous ones was false right because x and y was not equal so when you said x equal to
y it returns false but what if I say x not equal to y shall be printed see you get just the opposite
no you get true right because this is true now this is no this expression this logical expression
that we have written here boolean expression that is true because x and y is values are not same
so can we check the other so let me you know or check the next one so what if we write x
less than y so these are some you know like I mean you can assume that when you write x less than
y you're claiming that x is less than y but if this is not true no considering the current value
of your variables then the expression will evaluate to false right so in this example since x is
actually less than y so what do you expect if I again you know print this one what is the last
value that you have seen since x is less than you know y you see a value true okay so let me comment
the previous one so that there is no confusion okay so let's see if you print only you know this
one you see or you get a true value okay so again greater than is just opposite so you can just
change this to greater than in you see the answer should flip okay so it returns you a false value
okay so what about no less than equal to so in this case let's say if I have another
now very full set which again has the same value let's say 10 so what do you expect in print
so what shall I expect you know if I say x is less than equal to g let me comment out the
previous one just so if I you know print this what do you expect I mean will we get true or false at
this place true right because less than equal to means I mean either it should be less than or equal
to and here it written true because of no the you know equality thing right not to do less than
okay because when we say so if you print no x less than g let's say what do you think
you get a false right so this is not less than this but this is less than equal to
no less than or equal to g because of the no second thing being true that this is equal to j
so similarly I know you have no greater than equal to so we'll not know in the interest of time
we'll not just print it so you can just experiment with these things and now in all since you know
you know you can combine these things you know that you can combine and you know for you know complex
things also right because we know that you know these true and false can be combined using this
and an odd thing so now for just one more example I mean maybe let me comment this out
so what do you expect if I write you know print let's say x is less than equal to g or x is less than
g or y is
greater than g so what if we combine you know both these things so what we'll know this
evaluate to you know that this will no evaluate to false right because x is not less than g
but on the other hand you know that the right hand side of or y greater than g
in this case will evaluate to true and you know from our previous discussion right that if one
of no left hand side or right hand side of or is true then you know you get the value true right
so what you can expect here is a true value you see so this is how we can actually you know compare
the values of variable inside our program at a given point of time and we can also build complex
logic by you know comparing multiple things and combining them using these logical operators so
this is the advantage of having logical operator and comparison operator inside your programming
or language so that at any point of time if you want to take decision or if you know want to
you know create multiple branches at that particular point of time for executing different
some sort of things and you want to you know decide all of this based on some condition which
is complex condition on variable values then you can use this comparison operator as well as
logical operator to combine them effectively to get what you want okay more of it you know we will
see when we are come to or discuss these things okay so with this we know I would stop
you know this lecture we'll continue in the discussion of expression in the next video thank you
we'll see you in the next video